<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Our trust against trouble very expedient for the time, composed for our better consolation and consideration of these crosses of warre, lately attempted, and still intended against vs : with diuers speciall prayers and meditations, very requisite to be remembred of vs, before, in and after the time of our trouble / by Charles Gybbon.</title>
            <author>Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01680</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11818</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2684</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24497152</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24497152</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27735</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01680)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27735)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1852:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Our trust against trouble very expedient for the time, composed for our better consolation and consideration of these crosses of warre, lately attempted, and still intended against vs : with diuers speciall prayers and meditations, very requisite to be remembred of vs, before, in and after the time of our trouble / by Charles Gybbon.</title>
                  <author>Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Charlewood, dwelling in Barbican at the signe of the Halfe Eagle and the Key, and are there to be solde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Seene and allowed."</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁸.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers.</term>
               <term>Meditations.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27735:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Our truſt againſt <hi>trouble.</hi> Very expedient for the time, compoſed for our better conſolation, and conſideration of theſe croſſes of warre, lately attempted, and ſtill intended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs. <hi>With diuers ſpeciall prayers and Meditations, very requiſite to be remembred of vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in and after the time of our trouble.</hi> By Charles Gybbon.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. Eſdras. 16, 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>¶ Beholde famine, plague, trouble, and anguiſhe, are ſent as ſcourges for amendement.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Séene and allowed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>At London,</hi> Printed by Iohn Charlewood, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Barbican at the ſigne of the halfe Eagle and the Key, and are there to be ſolde. <hi>1589.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27735:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:27735:2"/>
            <head>To the right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sir Iohn Heigham Knight, long life and happy daies.</head>
            <p>THe proofe of your worships good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, hath made me preſume to preſent theſe my paines vnder your fauourable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection: not doubting, but as your worſhip is zealous in Religion, conformable in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and a ſupporter of godly enterpriſes, ſo you will become a Patron to any good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. Thus beeing lothe to trouble your patience with any prolixius or tedious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe not omitting my humble duetie, I commit your worſhip to the tuition of the Almightie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips to commaund. Charles Gibbon.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27735:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:27735:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:27735:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:27735:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:27735:5"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the courteous and Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>IF euery Chriſtian well conſidereth the courſe of his life, he ſhall finde it nothing els but a continuall warre, for the Spirite hath three carnall enemies which daily incounter with it, the fleſh world &amp; deuill, what more filthy then the fruites of the fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.13</note>If ye liue after the fleſh yee ſhall die what more wretched then the worke of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5, 19</note>The whole worlde lyeth in wicked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, what more deteſtable then the deedes of the deuill.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet, 5, 8,</note>As a roring Lyon hee goeth about ſeeking whom he may deuoure.</p>
            <p>Now if we will expell theſe enemies we muſt vſe theſe remedies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8, 13</note>If wee mortifie the deedes of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die we ſhall liue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1, Ioh. 5.5</note>If we beleeue that Ieſus is the ſonne of God, we ſhal ouercome this world</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 4.7</note>If we reſiſt the deuil he wil flie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27735:5"/> And no doubt theſe externall troubles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> war (wherewith we were lately viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) were ſent of God for our good, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tifie vs in this ſpiritual fight. For he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing the aduerſaries readye to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, did (by the ſame ſcourge) put vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mind of his indignation, becauſe we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ginne to faint in ſo good a fight. We <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue liued a long time in peace (the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord be praiſed for it and ſtill prolong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but wee haue abuſed this bleſſing,<note place="margin">Pſal. 30.6</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſaide in our proſperitie (as <hi>Dauid</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d) we ſhoulde not be mooued. Our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts haue lulled vs a ſleepe in ſecurity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e fleſhe hath followed all ſenſualitie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e worlde hath bewitched vs with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eere vanitie, and the deuill hath nuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d vs in iniquitie. Inſomuch that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as high time for the Lorde to touche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with theſe troubles, leaſt we had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hed in our ſinnes, and although hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th begunne very mildlie, in hope of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r conuerſion, we may be aſſured hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll proceede to puniſhe vs more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eamelie, if there be no reformation.</p>
            <p>Therfore now let vs learne to amend
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27735:6"/> our liues for feare of a further afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Let vs heare the word of God with more dilligence, and followe it in our life with more obedience, and though we liue in the fleſh,<note place="margin">2. Cor, 10, 3.</note> let vs not warre af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh. Though wee are in the world,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.31</note> let vs vſe it as though we vſed it not.<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.27.</note> Though the deuill dailie followe vs, let vs not giue place to him.</p>
            <p>Thus by reſiſting euill, wee ſhall grow in grace, and ſo by the meanes of our amendment, we ſhall pacifie the vvrath of God, and conſequentlie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the furie of our foes, which GOD graunt. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord, Charles Gibbon of <hi>Bury S. Edmond.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic_prayer">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:27735:6"/>
            <head>¶ A prayer for the good protection of our gracious Queene and Realme.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ternall good and gracious God,</l>
            <l>ſtretch forth thy ſauing hand:</l>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>et not our ſins prouoke thy wrath,</l>
            <l>but looke vpon this land.</l>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>n thee we doo repoſe our truſt,</l>
            <l>as one that neuer faile,</l>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ubuert both farre and fawning foes,</l>
            <l>they neuer may preuaile.</l>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>las what are we of our ſelues</l>
            <l>and want thee on our ſide,</l>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>ut euen as chaffe againſt the wind,</l>
            <l>not able to abide.</l>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>xtend therefore thy heauenly helpe,</l>
            <l>and though there be but ten,</l>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>hey ſhall affright ten thouſand foes,</l>
            <l>if thou doo ſay Amen.</l>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>aue mercy on vs all O Lord,</l>
            <l>For Chriſt our Sauiours ſake</l>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ccept our prayers in good part,</l>
            <l>and preſent pittie take.</l>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:27735:7"/>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>emember our good ſoueraigne Prince,</l>
            <l>thine owne annointed deere,</l>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>xpell her foes, increaſe her freends,</l>
            <l>no hurt may happen heere.</l>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>iue to her ſubiects faithfull harts,</l>
            <l>to loue her as they ought,</l>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>n any wiſe not to rebell,</l>
            <l>or thinke a wicked thought.</l>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>ot once to ſuffer or conſent</l>
            <l>to harme her anie way,</l>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>s we by duetie all are bound,</l>
            <l>becauſe ſhe is our ſtay.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:27735:7"/>
            <head>✿ An other godly Prayer verie good and neceſſarie to be vſed in theſe troubleſome dayes.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Eternall &amp; euerliuing Lord, although we thy wretches (by reaſon of our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold ſinnes and offences) are vnworthy to cry or call vpon thee for comfort, in theſe thy croſſes of tribulations come vppon vs: yet ſeeing (O Lord) thou haſt willed vs in our trouble to call vppon thee,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15</note> and thou wylt heare vs: and in the burden of our ſins to come vnto thee, and thou wilt eaſe vs,<note place="margin">Math. 11.28</note> wee preſume to proſtrate our humble prayers be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the throne of thy maieſtie, beſeeching thee of thy rich mercy in Chriſt, to forgyue our ſinnes, by thy daily renuing ſpirite, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our liues, and by thy fauourable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, to defende vs in theſe our troubles, that wee may not bee made a pray vnto the luſt of our enemies, wherby we may be made a reproch among thoſe prophane people, and thereby they may triumphe againſt thee in our ouerthrow, and ſay. <hi>Where is now their God.</hi> Confound and ſcatter (O Lord) theſe our enemies, in their impious enterpriſes and proceedings,<note place="margin">Gen, 11, 8</note> as thou diddeſt thoſe preſumptuous people at Babell. Infolde them in the folly of theyr filthy deuiſes, as thou diddeſt to <hi>Ahithophell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sa. 17.23</note> Infeeble theyr force, and ſmite them with thy Angell, as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27735:8"/> thou didſt the power of <hi>Saneherib</hi> In theyr terrible and deſperat attempts,<note place="margin">2. Re. 19.35</note> let them bee drowned, as was <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> Intrap &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them in their treaſons,<note place="margin">Exo. 14.16</note> as thou diddeſt <hi>Abſalom.</hi> Turne them (if any be to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted) as thou diddeſt <hi>Manaſſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 15 7</note> otherwiſe let them feele their due puniſhment, as did <hi>Corah</hi> and the reſt of his conſpiratours.<note place="margin">Num. 16.31</note> So we thy people and ſhéepe of thy paſture, ſhall prayſe thee for euer, and from generation to generation, wee will ſette foorth thy prayſe. Heare vs O mercifull Father, for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, our onely Mediator and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:27735:8"/>
            <head>A Shielde for a <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour.</hi> Selected out of the Scriptures, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning very neceſſarye Meditations, and prayers to be vſed in the time of trouble.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord it is nothing with thée to helpe with many or with no power.<note place="margin">2. Ch, 14.11</note> Help vs O Lord our God, for we reſt on thée, and in thy name are wee come againſt thys multitude. O Lorde thou art our God, let not man preuaile againſt thée.</p>
            <p>O our God wilt thou not iudge them,<note place="margin">2. Ch. 20.12</note> for there is no ſtrength in vs to ſtande before this great multitude y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commeth againſt vs, neither doo we know what to doo, but our eyes are toward thée.</p>
            <p>In God doo I truſt, I will not bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid what man can doo vnto mée.<note place="margin">Pſal. 56.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>O Lord our God, I beſeeche thee ſaue thou vs out of our enemies hand,<note place="margin">2. Re. 19.19.</note> that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27735:9"/> all the kingdomes of the earth may know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou O Lord art onely God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal, 25, 1, 2,</note>Vnto thée O Lorde, lift I vppe my ſoule, my God I truſt in thée, let mee not be confounded, let not mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies reioyce ouer mée.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 21.13</note>Be y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> exalted O lord in thy ſtrength, ſo ſhall wee ſing and praiſe thy power.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 22.4.5</note>Our fathers truſted in thée, they tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and thou didſt deliuer them. They called vpon thée &amp; were deliuered, they truſted in thee &amp; were not confounded.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 25.17.18.19.</note>The ſorrowes of my hart are inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, draw me out of my troubles, looke vpon my affliction, and my trauel, and forgiue all my ſins. Beholde mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies for they are many, and they hate me with carnall hatred.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 30.10</note>Heare O Lord and haue mercie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, Lord be thou mine helper.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.12</note>Giue me not vnto the luſt of my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 31.15.16</note>My times are in thy hande, deliuer me from the hands of my enemies, and from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that perſecute me, make thy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27735:9"/> face to ſhine vpon thy Seruant, and ſaue me through thy mercie.</p>
            <p>Our ſoule waiteth for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.20.</note> for hee is our help &amp; our ſhielde, let thy mercie O lord be vpon vs, as we truſt in thee.</p>
            <p>Plead thou my cauſe O lord with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſtriue with me,<note place="margin">Pſal. 35.1.2</note> fight thou againſt them that fight againſt me. Laie hande upon the ſhield and buckler and ſtande up for my help.</p>
            <p>Let not them that are mine enemies uniuſtlie triumph ouer me.<note place="margin">Pſal. 35.19</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let not them ſay in their harts,<note place="margin">Pſa. 35.25</note> O our ſoule reioyce, neither let them ſaie we haue deuoured him.</p>
            <p>Be mercifull vnto me O GOD,<note place="margin">Pſa. 56.1.2</note> for man wold ſwallow me vp, he fighteth continuallie and vexeth me.</p>
            <p>Mine enemies would daily ſwallow me vp, for manie fight againſt mee O thou moſt high.</p>
            <p>Haue mercy vppon me O God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.1</note> haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, for my ſoule truſteth in thée, &amp; in the ſhadow of thy wings will I truſt till theſe afflictions ouerpaſſe.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:27735:10"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 60.11.</note>Giue vs helpe againſt trouble, for vain is the help of man. Through God we ſhall doo valiantly, for he ſhal tread down our enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 70.1.2</note>O Lord haſt thee to deliuer me, make haſt to help me O lord. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded &amp; put to ſhame that ſéeke my ſoule, let them be turned backwarde and put to rebuke that deſire my hurt.</p>
            <p>Help vs O God of our ſaluation, for the glory of thy name and deliuer vs, and bée merciful vnto our ſins for thy names ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 36.1.2. Pſa. 79.6.9.</note>Powre out thy wrath vpon the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then that haue not known thée, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the kingdoms that haue not called vpon thy name. So we thy people and ſhéepe of thy paſture ſhall praiſe thee for euer, &amp; from generation to genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we will ſet forth thy praiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 86.1, 2</note>Incline thine eare O lord and heare me for I am poore and néedy. Preſerue thou my ſoule for I am mercifull, my God ſaue thy ſeruant that truſteth in thée. Be merciful vnto me O God, for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27735:10"/> I cry vpon thee continually.</p>
            <p>Reioyce the ſoule of thy ſeruaunt,<note place="margin">Pſa. 86, 4, 5 6, 17.</note> for vnto thée O lord doo I lift vp my ſoule.</p>
            <p>For thou Lord art good and merciful, and of great kindnes vnto all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that call vpon thée. Giue eare Lorde vnto my prayer, and harken to the voice of my ſupplication.</p>
            <p>Shewe a token of thy goodnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they which hate mee, may ſée it, and be aſhamed, becauſe thou O Lord haſt holpen and comforted me.</p>
            <p>O Lord heare my prayer and let my cry come vnto thee.<note place="margin">Pſa. 102.1, 2</note> Hide not thy face from me in the time of my trouble, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline thine eares vnto me, when I call make haſt to heare me.</p>
            <p>Helpe me O Lord my God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 109, 26, 27.</note> ſaue mée according to thy mercie. And they ſhal knowe that this is thy hande, and that thou O Lord haſt doone it.</p>
            <p>Our help is in the name of the Lord which hath made heauen and earth.<note place="margin">Pſa. 124, 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Deliuer me O Lord from mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies for I hide me with thee.<note place="margin">Pſal. 143.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:27735:11"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 144.11 12.</note>And for thy mercie ſlay mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, &amp; deſtroy all them that oppreſſe my ſoule, for I am thy ſeruant.</p>
            <p>Reſcue mee and deliuer me from the hands of Strangers, whoſe mouth tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vanitie, and their right hande is a right hand of falſhood. That our Sons may be as the plants growing vppe in their youth, and our Daughters as the corner ſtones, grauen after the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of a Pallace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 144.13.14, 15</note>That our corners may be ful, aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with diuers ſortes, and that our ſheepe may bring forth thouſands and ten thouſands in our ſtreets.</p>
            <p>That our Oxen may be ſtrong to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, that there be no inuaſion, nor go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, nor crying in our ſtreetes.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed are the people that be ſo, yea bleſſed are the people whoſe God is the Lorde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:27735:11"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Our truſt againſt trouble.</head>
            <p>¶ That vvee may the more patientlie, thankfully, and ioyfully carry &amp; ouercome the croſſe of tribulation &amp; trouble. Let vs firſt of all conſider who is the Author of it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>1. It is God that ſendeth warre.</head>
               <p>AND that is approoued vnto vs in theſe words. <hi>Beholde nowe for I, I am he, and there is no Gods with me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deu. 32.39</note> 
                  <hi>I kill and I giue life, I wounde &amp; I make whole, neither is there any that can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer out of my hand.</hi> The <hi>Iſralites</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed all their afflictions to come from God. <hi>Come</hi> (ſay they) <hi>let vs returne to the Lord:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſea, 6, 1</note> 
                  <hi>for he hath ſpoyled and hee will heale vs, he hath wounded vs, &amp; he will bind vs vp. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that we may learne by this, two profitable inſtructions.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Albeit the wicked doo make war, wée muſt not ſuppoſe they doo it of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, for God doth after a ſort vſe and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:27735:12"/> ſend them as his ſeruaunts, (and ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie fitly calleth them) becauſe hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them to ſerue him by conſtraint, and that which they doo of malice, hee turneth to his honor and glory, as hee did by <hi>Nebuchadnezer,</hi> who when he beſieged <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> hee did it not of hys own accorde, for the Lorde had ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>I will ſende <hi>Nebuchadnezer</hi> my Seruaunt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere, 25, 9</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Although our enemies attempt to trouble vs, yet this is our aſſurance, they can procéede no further then God will permit or appoint them, becauſe they are but as inſtruments to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his indignation.<note place="margin">Eſay, 10, 5,</note>
               </p>
               <p>Sith it is God that ſendeth warre, we are next to conſider wherfore or for what cauſe hee dooth commonly vſe to ſend it, for he neuer ſendeth his viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in vaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>2 Warre is ſent as a ſcourge for ſinne.</head>
               <p>And that may appeare vnto vs by this ſentence.<note place="margin">Pſal. 89, 31,</note> 
                  <hi>If they breake my ſtatutes &amp; keepe not my commaundements, then
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27735:12"/> will I viſit their tranſgreſſion with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d &amp; their iniquitie with ſtrokes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And may further prooued to vs in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſe places.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Leu. 26, verſe, 17</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Deut. 28, verſe, 20, 22</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2, Chro. 20, verſe, 9</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Iewes</hi> attributed all their afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons to their ſinnes.<note place="margin">Baru. 2, 5, 6</note>
               </p>
               <p>The ſins which ſo prouoke the Lord puniſh vs, no doubt are theſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anie other.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſe of his worde. </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ontempt of his Miniſt. </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouetouſnes. </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tortion.</item>
                  <item>Pryde.</item>
                  <item>Whoredome.</item>
                  <item>Drunkennes, and ſuch like.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe and ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſins raigned in <hi>Iſraell, Ieruſalem, and Iudah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For which ſins the Lord did ſend his worde amongſt them, as you may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad at large, in <hi>Eſay. 28. Eze. 22. Iere. 5.</hi> So that wee may obſerue in this, bee ſpeciall conſiderations.</p>
               <p>That we muſt not take theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to come of courſe, but acknowledg <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſins to be the cauſe, and therby we all perceiue that God by ſending the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th ſéeke nothing but our good, premo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing vs gently, leaſt wee perriſh in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:27735:13"/> our ſin ſecurely.<note place="margin">2, Eſd. 16, 15</note> 
                  <hi>Behold famine, plague trouble, and anguiſh, are ſent as ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for amendement.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro, 3, 12,</note> 
                  <hi>For whom God ſcourgeth he loueth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> That if we ſhew an vnfained con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and make a true and harty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition for our ſins, leading our liues in better obedience of the worde of God, theſe troubles ſhalbe taken away from vs. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde hath ſaid to thoſe that doo ſo,<note place="margin">Leu, 26.6, 7</note> 
                  <hi>I wil ſend peace in your land, yee ſhall ſleepe &amp; none ſhall make you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, &amp; the ſword ſhal not goe throg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> your land, yee ſhal chaſe your enemies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and they ſhall fall before you vpon the ſword, &amp; fiue of you ſhal chaſe an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, &amp; an hundred of you ſhal put ten thouſand to flight, &amp; your enemy ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fal before you vpon the ſword.</hi> For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord taketh no pleaſure in the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſinners,<note place="margin">2, Chr, 12, 12 Ezek, 18, 32</note> but in their conuerſion</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> That if wee ſtill perſeuere in ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſins without repentaunce (making <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> account of this milde correction latel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſent vs)<note place="margin">Rom, 2, 5</note> we ſhall not onelie heape vnt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:27735:13"/> our ſelues wrathe againſt the daie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dgment, but alſo in this life,<note place="margin">Leu, 26, 16 Nehe, 9, 28</note> procure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Lorde to puniſhe vs ſeauen times more according to our ſins, and make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im giue vs ouer vnto the luſt of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emies. (which God defend.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>3. How we ought to remedy and defend theſe afflictions.</head>
               <p>In that they come of God and not of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an, wee may learne thrée ſinguler leſſons.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> That we muſt not altogether de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ende vppon the ordinary and lawfull meanes as Men, Munition, Worldlie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower and Pollicie, for that is abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation in the ſight of God, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that which is pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Iſralites, <hi>Woe vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that goe downe into Egipt for helpe,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay, 31, 1,</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ſtay vpon Horſſes &amp; truſt in Charrets, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are many, &amp; in horſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are very ſtrong, but they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ooke not vnto the holy one of Iſraell, nor ſeeke vnto the Lorde.</hi> And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward there is produced a reaſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:27735:14"/> them. <hi>The Egiptians are men &amp; not gods,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay, 31, 3,</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; their horſes fleſhe and not ſpirit, &amp; when the lord ſhal ſtretch out his hand, the helper ſhall fall, &amp; he that is holpen ſhall fal, and they ſhal altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faile.</hi> And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſaith. <hi>Curſed be the man that truſteth in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere, 17, 5</note> 
                  <hi>and maketh fleſh his arme, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draweth his hart from the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg, 20, 20.</note> The ſame <hi>Iſralites</hi> truſting in their ſtrength were diſcomfited by the <hi>Beniamites,</hi> for it is written.<note place="margin">1, Sam, 2, 9</note> 
                  <hi>In his owne might ſhall no man be ſtrong.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> That as wee muſt not neglect the inſtrumental &amp; lawful remedy to with ſtand the aduerſary. So we ought eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to reſpecte the efficient cauſe, (which is God) who ſendeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemie, remembring what the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that maketh the lord his truſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal, 40, 41 Iere, 17, 17</note> 
                  <hi>for God can aſwel without as with weapon, terrifie &amp; deſtroy the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2, Chr, 14, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Abiiah</hi> making war againſt <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam,</hi> got the victory not altogether with the multitude of men. But it is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:27735:14"/> there ſaid, hee did the rather preuaile, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecauſe he and his ſtaied vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od of their fathers.<note place="margin">2, Chr, 13, 18</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inſt <hi>Goliah,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> huge Giant, although <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e did not contemne the Armour King <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aul</hi> put vpon him, yet (becauſe he could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot away withal) hee did not weare it. Notwithſtanding, betaking himſelf to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s ſling, and committing his truſt in God, hée ouercame his enemie, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Lord will haue his power knowne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> preuaile. Aſſuring vs thereby,<note place="margin">1, Sam, 17 51, 54,</note> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wee fight in faith vnder his defence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e will neuer faile vs.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> That we muſt both fight with our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ndes and pray with our harts toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her, following the good example of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>refathers in their afflictions.<note place="margin">1, Sam, 7, 8, 9</note> The Children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> did not onelie fight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> but requeſted <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muell</hi> (that notable Prophet) to cry vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the Lord for them.<note place="margin">2, Ch, 20, 12,</note> 
                  <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng againſt his enemies, did withſtand with weapon &amp; proſtrate his Prayer. <hi>Aſa</hi> warring againſt the <hi>Ethiopians;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2, Ch, 14, 11</note> did
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:27735:15"/> both reſiſt with weapon, and perſiſt in prayer, for as we muſt not omitte the lawful ordinaunce (God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) to defend vs. So we muſt commit our ſelues to him, who giueth the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, &amp; ſubmit both to his protection.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>4. Howe wee may take comfort in theſe croſſes of trouble.</head>
               <p>Let vs but conſider what moueth the enemy to intermeddle with vs.</p>
               <p>Surely nothing els but ſiniſter occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as ſome of theſe enſuing.</p>
               <p>Pretending,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1. To hurt our ſoueraigne Queene the Lordes annointed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2. To hinder the free paſſage of Gods word amongſt vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3. To deſtroye the little flocke of Gods folde in this land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4. To ſette abroche all ſuperſtition and abhomination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No doubt as their intent is euill, ſo their ſucceſſe will be ſuch.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Exo, 14, 16</note>
                  <hi>Paraoh</hi> (that tiranicall rebellor) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king warre againſt the <hi>Iſralites</hi> (that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:27735:15"/> choſen people of GOD) could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile,<note place="margin">2, Ch. 20, 22</note> for the Lord drowned him and al his hoſte in the Sea.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Moabites</hi> &amp; <hi>Amonites</hi> (that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe &amp; wretched people) making war againſt <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good King of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi>) they were ſo far from ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming that one enemy did helpe to deſtroy an other of his aduerſaries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sanaherib</hi> that great blaſphemer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king war againſt <hi>Hezekiah</hi> that godlie Prince,<note place="margin">2, Re, 19, 35.</note> had ſo good ſucceſſe in his enter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>priſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Angel of the Lord went out and in one night ſmote in the Campe, an hundred, foureſcore and fiue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of his men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zerah</hi> of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2, Chr, 14 12, 13,</note> making warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt King <hi>Aſa,</hi> was ſo farre from gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ouerthrow, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he and his were enforced to flie, &amp; receiue the foyle.</p>
               <p>Thus we may ſée by theſe examples that although God will ſometime pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his children for their ſins, by ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the nenemy to aſſault them, yet hee will not permit the enemy to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:27735:16"/> ouer his people, ſo they repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and be ſory for their ſins, &amp; repoſe their truſt in their troubles vnder hys defence.</p>
               <p>Let vs not be terrified becauſe of the multitude of men, but let vs reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that notable ſaying of <hi>Aſa</hi> in his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,<note place="margin">2, Ch, 14, 11</note> 
                  <hi>Lorde it is nothing with thee to help with many or with no power.</hi> For no doubt we may ſay of our enemy (as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did of <hi>Sancherib, <hi>With him is an arme of fleſh, but with vs is the lord our God, for to helpe vs and to fight our battels.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let vs pray without diſpaire, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering what the Lord hath ſaid.<note place="margin">Pſal. 50, 15</note> 
                  <hi>Call vpon mee in the time of trouble, and I will heare thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exo, 17, 11</note> When <hi>Moyſes</hi> lyfted vp his hand, <hi>Iſraell</hi> preuailed, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he let downe his hand, the <hi>Amalekites</hi> preuailed, teaching vs thereby to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and perſeuere in our prayers, without fainting, <hi>for the Lorde is nigh to all thoſe that call vpon him in fayth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal, 145, 18,</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>5. How we ought to behaue our ſelues af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter troubles for the good ſucceſſe is ſent vs.</head>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:27735:16"/>
               <p>We muſt offer to God the Sacrifice of prayſe and thankſgiuing.</p>
               <p>As the Lorde hath promiſed in our troubles to heare &amp; helpe vs, ſo he hath ſaid. <hi>Thou ſhalt praiſe me. For of him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal, 50, 15 Rom, 11, 36,</note> 
                  <hi>through him &amp; for him are all things, to him be glory.</hi> Leaſt if we forgette or neglect to bee thankfull to him for his benefits, he doth further afflict vs. For it is ſaid of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> (after God had wonderfully deliuered him from hys enemies) that he did not render accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reward beſtowed vpon him, for his hart was lift vp,<note place="margin">2, Ch, 32, 25</note> and therefore the wrathe of God came againſt him vpon <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therfore that we may the more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually offer our prayſes to God, let vs obſerue two things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration. Of the oppoſite daunger of our enemie with our ſafe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerie.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Of our vnwoorthy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, with Gods wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mercie.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In ſo dooing we ſhall find Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:27735:17"/> ſo ſuperaboundant, and our deſerts ſo repugnaunt, that euery one of vs, in the end of our troubles, ſhall be enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſay as <hi>Dauid</hi> did,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 116.12, 13, 17</note> 
                  <hi>What ſhall I render vnto the Lorde for all his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites towards mee? I will take the Cup of ſaluation and call vppon the name of the Lord. I will offer to him a ſacrifice of prayſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gen, 14, 19</note>
                  <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> gaue thanks for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> victory.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Exo, 15, 1, 2</note>
                  <hi>Moyſes</hi> and the <hi>Iſralites</hi> ſong prayſes for their deliueraunce.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg, 5, 1, 2</note>So did <hi>Deborah, Barak</hi> and dyuers others.</p>
               <p>For if the Lorde ſmelled a ſauour of reſt at the burnt offering of <hi>Noah,</hi> how acceptable wil our praiſes be, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede from a contrite hart, ſith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde himſelfe ſaith:<note place="margin">Pſal, 50, 23</note> 
                  <hi>Hee that offereth mee prayſe ſhall glorifie me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:27735:17"/>
            <head>A tryumphe after <hi>trouble.</hi> Contayning a prayſe or thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, fit for euery Chriſtian to offer and confeſſe to God, for the benefite of their deliuerance.</head>
            <head type="sub">Collected out of the Scriptures.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Will magnifie thée O Lorde,<note place="margin">Pſal, 30, 1</note> for thou haſt exalted mee, and haſt not made my foes to reioyce ouer me.</p>
            <p>By this O Lord I knowe that thou fauoureſt me,<note place="margin">Pſal, 41, 11,</note> becauſe my enemy doth not tryumphe againſt me.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt turned my mourning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ioy,<note place="margin">Pſal, 30, 11</note> thou haſt looſed my ſacke &amp; gyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me with gladnes. Therefore ſhall my tongue prayſe thée, and not ceaſe: O Lorde my God I will giue thankes vnto thée for euer.</p>
            <p>I will alwaies giue thanks vnto the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſalm, 34 1, 2, 3, 4</note> his praiſe ſhall bee in my mouth continually, my ſoule ſhall glory in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:27735:18"/> Lord, the humble ſhall heare it and be glad. Praiſe ye the Lord with me and let vs magnifie his name together. I ſought the Lord and he heard me, yea he deliuered mee out of all my feare.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm, 44, 5 6, 7, 8,</note>Through thée haue we thruſt backe our aduerſaries, by thy name haue wée troden downe them that roſe vppe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, for I do not truſt in my bow neither can my ſword ſaue mee. But thou haſt ſaued vs from our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and haſt put them to confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hate vs.<note place="margin">Pſal. 56, 12</note> Therfore will we praiſe God continually, and wil confeſſe his name for euer.</p>
            <p>Thy vowes are vpon me O GOD, I will render praiſe vnto thée.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal, 59, 16,</note>I will ſing of thy power and praiſe thy mercy in the morning, for thou haſt beene my defence and refuge in the day of my trouble.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal, 63, 5, 6</note>My ſoule ſhall be ſatiſ-fied as wyth marowe &amp; fatnes, and my mouth ſhall praiſe thée with ioyful lips, when I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thée on my bed, and when I
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:27735:18"/> think vpon thee in the night watches, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt béene my helper, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnder the ſhadowe of thy winges will I reioyce.</p>
            <p>I loue the Lorde becauſe hee hath heard my voice and my prayers.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 116 1, 17, 18,</note> I wil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffer to thée a ſacrifice of praiſe &amp; wyll call vpon the name of the Lord. I wyll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay my vowes vnto the lord, euen now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the preſence of all his people.</p>
            <p>The Lord is my ſtrength and ſong,<note place="margin">Pſal, 118, 14,</note> for he hath béene my deliueraunce.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed bee the Lorde my ſtrength,<note place="margin">Pſa, 144, 1, 2</note> which teacheth my hands to fight, and my fingers to battell, he is my goodnes and my fortreſſe my Towre &amp; my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerer, my ſhield and in him I truſt.</p>
            <p>If the Lord had not béene on our ſide when men roſe vp againſt vs,<note place="margin">Pſal, 123, 1, 2</note> they had then ſwallowed vs vp quicke, when their wrath was kindled againſt vs.</p>
            <p>Prayſed bee the Lorde which hath not giuen vs,<note place="margin">Pſal, 124, 6</note> as a praye vnto theyr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeth. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
